e
e e
[Music]
e
good evening everyone uh I'm calling the
finance committee meeting for September
9th 2024 to order and it is
6:00 and um it's going to be a short
meeting in
that first time who knows when if ever
no resolutions to be brought before
council tonight and we have two Ord es
uh the first ordinance is temporary
ordinance
32-24 an ordinance to accept the
annexation of
5.0 plus or minus acres in Pleasant
Township and to declare an emergency uh
this is coming from Council as a whole
and I believe uh councilman skover is
going to talk about
it I am awesome would you like me to
address it councilman skover
yeah it's just the final piece of the
annexation correct yes so there's a
60-day waiting period between when the
County Commissioners Grant the petition
for annexation and when we're allowed to
accept it um that date was up on
September 7th so this was your next
regularly planned meeting and that's why
it's before you tonight we'd like to get
it done with one reading um because
there are multiple developers speaking
with um Stephanie Bosco at the Port
Authority about about getting this
developed for residential uh housing
multif family and single family um so we
want to keep it moving if we possibly
can thank you so I will ask for
suspension uh with Mrs Miss Tiner as my
second any questions any concerns about
suspension great we'll move on to
Temporary ordinance
33-24 an ordinance ordinance to
authorize the mayor to acquire five
permanent drainage easements necessary
for the East Main Street sewer
separation and and Court during each
Improvement phase one project coming
from water water P control uh councilman
wi uh yes thank you Mr
chairman we have as many of you probably
recognize this we've discussed this
project quite a bit here in Council and
the city needs to obtain five easements
on five different properties in order to
um carry out this project so I want to
invite uh stepen to come up and speak to
that thank you councilman good evening
everybody um so yeah as noted again uh
this East Main Street sewer separation
and Court drainage project I've been up
here a few times with regards to that
project so won't rehash any of that but
um we are going through private property
or in one case very close to private
property and and that necessitates an
easement for us on this project so I
reached out to the five Property Owners
we need um easements from they're all in
general agreement uh so once I got that
confirmation uh you know prepared this
legislation to go before you to get
approved and then uh our plan would be
to move forward with getting those
executed once approval is granted if
there's any questions I'd certainly be
happy to answer
them any
questions all right council member alss
will be my second and we'll go a full
three readings full three
readings and that uh approves the
ordinances and we'll move on to uh
departmental updates
good evening chairman president members
of council here is the um Municipal
Arbus this evening I understand you
probably have received some concerns
about some trees that the tree
commission or the municipal arborist and
the City forest are removed up on
Chestnut Street East Chestnut in front
of Firehouse Park so I'm here to uh give
you an explanation of how that decision
was reached and why the trees were
removed and what the plan is for a
replacement there there was five trees
along the front of the sidewalk in about
a 3-ft tree lawn area which we would
normally never plant trees in because
it's too small a space for a large tree
in that area the parks department over
the years has received several
complaints about that sidewalk requested
to have it replaced we actually found
the money in the budget it was not a
budgeted process project this year but
we had enough money to go ahead and move
ahead with that so as the municipal
arborist I asked the city Forester to go
up and assess those trees um he was
directed when he went up there to do
everything in his power to find a way to
save the
trees when he assessed them he
determined that the trees probably would
die would not be able to be saved
because of the process of the removal of
the actual sidewalk itself so to explain
um if you plant a tree and I'm going to
use an analogy here so forgive me so if
you plant a tree in your yard a tree's
got a good base it's got four directions
it can send roots out in um it's got a
good base to to be able to grow in um
Street trees because of their very
nature especially in a very narrow Tree
Lawn like there is up there in front of
the park um basically grow in two
directions they can grow back towards
the park away from the street and they
can grow along the street so when if
you've ever watched sidewalk removal
they use equipment to pull the old
sidewalk up and when they do that tears
all of the roots along they up with that
sidewalk when that happens um the tree
loses half B basically 50% of its
support base for the most part um so
imagine the analogy I use is it's like
making a person stand on one foot so
most likely what happens on average the
tree usually dies um and because we know
it's be going to become hazardous for
Windstorm wind events High storm events
that is eventually going to fall land in
the street land in the park land some
somewhere um we usually make the choice
to go ahead and remove the tree
proactively and then go back and replace
them so that was the that was the logic
behind the decision um that's what drove
the decision and that's why those trees
were removed we do have a replacement
plan we've had a replacement plan in
place before we even really started to
move forward with it so in that tree
lawn the other the other issue I didn't
mention with those those five trees was
there's actually overhead utility lines
there it's very small ones that there is
utility service that goes through there
the trees were in the utility service
already a had also contacted us about
adding additional service so we were
going to have to heavily trim those
trees back anyway to get the utility
lines in if AAP puts them in so again
another another concern there
replacement plan involves going back in
with a smaller variety of tree we have
not selected it yet but in that smaller
tree lawn we'll put a smaller tree that
doesn't grow as tall so it won't involve
utilities should not damage any new
sidewalk that's put in and then on the
park side where there's more room for
those trees to grow we're going to go up
the hills there's a slope if you've not
been up there we're planning on going up
that slope halfway maybe a bit more
planting a larger variety of tree that
will grow taller will stay out of the
utility lines and provide shade for the
park so um my goal when we're done and I
can't promise it but my goal when we're
done done as we'll actually have more
trees in place there than we do now
they'll be younger they won't be as big
but they'll grow and they'll be in place
for probably a longer time so so there
you go that was what drove the decision
I apologize that you all had um I know
you've had concerns brought to you
because I've talked to several of you
about it yes sir you mentioned the
reason one of the reasons was the the
equipment that they used to remove the
sidewalk yes describe that um it I
believe they used a mini EX in this case
and what they do is they hook underneath
the sidewalk and they drag the drag the
the old pieces up and then they use a a
front loader to load it into the truck
so let me ask you this can you specify
in situations like this that they take
more care in the equipment that they use
can you say to them I don't want you to
use that that piece of equipment I want
you to remove it by I want you to use a
sledgehammer um we could do that but
that would drive the cost cost of the
project up considerably okay um if you
do it by hand it's that's one of the
things that does you know is it is a
budget concern it is a resource concern
for us so it's we're
we're that piece of your explanation is
the only one that really causes me
concern because if I had a tree that I
wanted to save I would tell the people
that were removing the sidewalk how to
not how to do their jobs but I would
have hope that I would have discovered a
better way to I don't want to I don't
want to ruin the tree I don't want to
ruin a tree on my property so I'm going
to find a way to remove the sidewalk
without tearing up the tree yeah that's
that's really all I want to say yeah and
I do understand that I I do think
without the utility lines and without
the the other pieces involved with that
the fact that the trees had already
outgrown the space they were in we we
could have looked at something like that
we did discuss several options we
discussed trying to shave the roots
which would have meant we would have
been much more careful you know with
pulling that out but in looking at not
all the trees but most of them that was
not going to we did not believe that was
going to be workable um so again it is
we we do take all that in consideration
when we make these
decisions thank so what you're saying
then is that these trees were of a
species that the roots typically are
just underneath the surface of the
ground because SL sidewalks only 4 in
deep mhm I we we live on Allen Street we
got 60t tall trees in our front yard in
that little lawn space we replaced our
entire sidewalk the trees are fine so
and but we did Jackhammer that they did
Jackhammer it they didn't get a front
end loader in there yeah but I you know
Roots do grow a lot deeper than 4 Ines
on most trees so I don't think you would
be destroying all the root system for
those trees just by simply pulling the
sidewalk that's just just a thought okay
any other
questions
input thank you thank you
everyone uh any any other departmental
updates to come
forth I see none and I'll turn it over
to uh president Porter for tonight's uh
prep yes we have uh one special
presentation tonight auditor Nettles do
we have the gentleman who's coming
tonight to do the presentation
yes I don't see he you well we do have a
special presentation tonight from the
state auditor's office if they do happen
to come and um that's
it do we have a new clerk official yes
well it's officially well we we were
gonna wait till the regular meeting but
we will do it now yes we do have a new
clerk would you like to introduce
yourself my name is anit Scott and I am
with the city of Lancaster um I work in
the auditor's office as Trish's
assistant
and I'm going to do this on the side and
help you guys out so thank you very much
for taking up the torch sorry Mr
President I you're you're all good I was
this is the meeting prep so I fig I'll
introduce it later we've all got it done
thank you appreciate it uh no other
comments I think you're looking for
stuff to add to the agenda I'm looking
for other items for finance
committee hearing none I would entertain
a motion for adjournment make a motion
to adjourn wait well we're doing meeting
prep after did you yeah we're done made
oh okay I didn't know you said um I
didn't realize you I actually have
something oh I'm so sorry okay so um
temporary resolution
8524 which deals with giving money to
the dog
shelter uh do we know when they're
coming oh Carrie oh she's in the back I
thought I saw you walk in do we know
when they're coming to do their
presentation it'll be in
September I will defer to president
it'll be in September okay well I at
this time um just so I know there are
some issues I have questions them I
actually would like to have 8524 table
tonight until they come in and talk to
us and we have questions for them they
can answer and if it isn't going to be
tabled and go through I I will be voting
no on it okay
that was uh what number I'm sorry
8524 thank you any
other
questions comments now I will look for a
motion you I'll make a motion to adjourn
second all the well you're yes yes yes
we are dismissed we
dismissed at 612
what time will the meeting
[Music]
hi this is Chuck Sims with the Lancaster
dare program dare provides students with
skills to resist the pressure of drugs
gangs and violence and emphasizes
self-esteem good decisionmaking and
communication skills this month when you
buy a car truck or SUV from Buckeye
Toyota or bucke bu eyee Honda the
Buckeye cares program will make a
generous donation to DARE with every
vehicle they sell thanks Buckeye for
your continued support and helping keep
our kids
safe the Frankie Smith Funeral Home in
cremator in Lancaster and the Johnson
Smith Funeral Home in Baltimore have a
long and wonderful history of serving
our community feel free to give us a
call at
0652 stop at and see us at either of our
two locations 405 North Columbus Street
in Lancaster and 207 South Main Street
in Baltimore respect for tradition
regard for change
[Music]
e
e e
join us in a moment of prayer God grant
us the serenity to accept the things we
cannot change the courage to to change
the things we can and finally the wisdom
to know the difference please join me in
the Pledge of Allegiance I now call the
city council meeting to
order pledge aliance to the flag of the
United States of America and to the
Republic for which it stands one nation
under God indivisible with liy and
justice for all
can we please call the
RO Mr
ALS here Mr aers here Mr bisj here Mrs
CH here Mrs hoop here Mrs Mr lenberg
here Mr skover here M here Mr Wing here
and Mr wolfinger
pres let let us let the record note that
all 10 members of Lancaster City Council
are present
we'll now move on to the reading and
disposing of the journal regular meeting
minutes dated o August 26
2024 the the clerk presented the regular
meeting minutes dated August 26 2024 Mr
sco am I reading that
right okay sorry Mr President i' like to
make a motion to receive and file the
journal second we have a motion and
second to receive and file the journal
all those in favor please uh say I I all
those oppose same
sign reports of City
officials um email dated August 27th
2024 regarding finance committee minuts
submitted by Mr wolfinger email dated
August 29 2024 regarding service
committee
agenda uh submitted by Mr ALS email
dated September 4th 2024 regarding the
income tax taxes August collection
report report submitted by Tax
Commissioner Hamilton email dated
September 8th 2024 regarding finance
committee minutes submitted by Mr
wolfer Mr President I'd like to make a
motion to receive and follow reports of
City officials second we have a motion
and second to receive and file the
reports of City officials all those in
favor please stay I I all those opposed
same
sign now move on to Communications email
dat is September 4th 2024 regarding tree
remove removal at Firehouse Park
submitted by Chelsea
der Mr President I'd like to make a
motion to receive and follow the
communications second we have a motion
and second to receive and file the
communications all those in favor please
note by saying I I I all those oppose
same
sign we will now move on to special
presentation and awards and we do have a
representative from the auditor of State
here uh this evening if you'd like to
approach the podium and introduce your
yourself yes thank you um and thank you
for your time uh and giving me a few
minutes on your agenda this evening to
speak my name is Scott Brown I represent
um state auditor Keith Faber as his
Central Ohio liaison what that means to
you and more importantly um people like
your auditor is that I serve as her
customer service representative so
hopefully I'm her first call when she
had other than on audit issues um when
she has a question from her office um
and I can give you Disney Disney like
service um uh to to get things moving
again in in the city but it is my
pleasure and honor to be here this
evening on behalf of auditor Faber to
present city of Lancaster with the
auditor of State Award with
distinction this award puts your city in
a very select group of the nearly 4,200
entities that we audit every year less
than 4% are eligible for this award
the auditor of State Award with it with
distinction is presented to local
governments school districts and other
entities upon the completion of a
financial audit that meet these criteria
to be considered a clean audit report
whereas I like to say a very short
letter from our office um The Entity
must file Financial reports with the
auditor's office by a statutory due date
without extension on a gap accounting
basis and prepare a comprehensive annual
financial
report the audit does not contain any
fin ings for Recovery material citations
material weaknesses significant
deficiencies uniform guidance finding or
other question
costs breaking through all the audit
speak what this really means is this
award represents the hard work of all of
the city of Lancaster staff and
employees who make every effort each day
to attain accounting Excellence we'd
like to recognize the council the
administration and the finance office
that have done an outstanding job
watching over every dollar what this
truly means is that it across your
entire organization you have the people
and processes in place that understand
fiscal accountability spec specifically
we want to recognize Trisha Nettles for
her leadership professionalism and
exception exceptional commitment so on
behalf of auditor Faber I'd like to
present the city of Lancaster the
auditor of State Award with distinction
congratulations and I can answer any
questions Trisha this is where you come
from
[Applause]
they're taking
pictures thank
[Music]
you we thank you Mr Brown uh we
appreciate this um auditor Nettles do
you have anything you'd like to add this
evening that's what I said okay thank
yes um thank you so much um this again I
I'm I'm honored to do this this is a lot
of hard work from a lot of people in the
city from my staff that get on I think
every Department's nerves of asking for
all the little details and
nuances to to satisfy the state
auditor's office but also again for the
Departments that put the stuff and put
up with us so we can do our due
diligence and be very fiscal with our
money so again thanks to all of my staff
and everybody else that complies with
what we ask thank you we thank you and
uh any council members have any comment
or okay well thank you very much we
appreciate
it um we also have one other spe special
presentation this evening it's a less
formal one and I would ask U Miss tener
to join me in this we are going to be um
wishing council member um aers
happy birthday because we missed his
birthday was last week so will you start
us off on singing happy
birthday you got the mic anybody got a
shot around here I can start singing you
got the M okay
everybody happy birthday to
youth happy birthday to you happy
birthday dearth
birthday to
you thank
you you going to tell us how many he can
he's young enough
2 sucks that
old well congratulations we we
appreciate all the work you do here and
uh happy birthday thank you all thank
you so petitions and memorials there are
no petitions or memorials this evening
okay so at this time we've reached the
point of the evening that we have
permission of Voters and taxpayers to
address city council we've talked
briefly about it earlier and I know that
I saw some folks signing up on the uh
signin sheet you have three minutes once
you reach the podium and we will be
keeping that time and I will also um ask
once again that you identify your name
and your address uh when you come up to
the podium so I'm sorry can I I thought
we went to from 3 to 5 minutes did we
not do that or was that just in public
hearings yeah we're three I've always
done three okay is that okay yeah I just
didn't know I thought it would
okay okay so is anybody coming
forward good
evening uh my name is Chuck beron I live
at 346 booving Road I'm also the
executive director of the Fairfield
Family
Forum and I thank you for the
opportunity to address the
council our mission is to serve our
communities through education and
protection of our traditional Family
Values thank you we believe the backbone
of our society is a strong family values
and the success of our communities with
each of Lies with each of us coming
together to defend and promote these
values it's been brought to our
attention by the citizens of our
community that a local establishment
known as the faux bar has had one event
on the 21st and is now promoting another
one this Friday called drag out your
pride which is a drag queen ex
exhibition selling tickets for the show
and then on Saturday spilling out into
the square it has come to our attention
that the establishment intends to do
these on a quarterly basis even more
concerning are the entities supporting
this event the Fairfield County Health
Department the library destination
downtown New Horizons and the Fairfield
Democratic party to name a few our tax
dollars are used to support these this
abomination in our community these
events are in direct violation of
several ordinances passed by the city of
Lancaster including chapter 1139 and
chapter 531 we believe this poses a
potential danger within our community
and we have and will have a negative
effect on our community
standers we believe this type of public
exhibition not only violates the spirit
and the letter of the these ordinances
it also does not meet the long-held
community standards our citizens have
enjoyed for many years as a strong
Christian populous the influx of this
type of lewd and obscene Behavior gives
many in our community pause to how safe
we and our children are with the influx
of this deviant behavior in our
city we are requesting that the council
take immediate action to enforce the
city code and to Hal further lwen OB
seed exhibitions in this and any other
establishment in the city though crude
these types of pornographic events and
parades are philosophical statements it
says there are no rules about sex sex is
Trivial and sex is for entertainment
though debase these types of events are
a theological statement it says there is
no God who says we should put limits on
our lust or Channel our passions
pornographic events like this is
anti-woman anti- child anti anti-
marriage anti- permanence and thus
profoundly anti-
civilization since civilization is a
social support to the Dynamics of Life
pornography is
anti-life even a casual reading of
History tells us that when a society
turns away from the teachings and
morality of the Holy Scripture and we
have lost our fear of God Empires fall I
don't know if this is the ending of our
age but I what I do know if we don't
change our Behavior it will be the end
of our
Republic I will leave you with this
quote from Edmund Burke the only thing
necessary for the Triumph of evil is for
good men to do
nothing I believe the only I believe you
are all honorable men and women and will
do the right thing to protect our
children and our families and give us
important issue your immediate attention
and action and once again I thank you
for your attention and pray for your
immediate attention in this matter thank
you thank
you good evening mayor council members
my name is Brian Everett uh a live at
2011 South High Street having been to a
number of drag shows throughout uh this
state this country and this world I am
surprised to hear uh that none of them
were nearly as entertaining as they were
purported to be by the previous speaker
uh they are simply adults doing what
adults are allowed to do Under The
Republic terminations of which our
country was founded namely the First
Amendment which allows for freedom of
speech directs that no government shall
abridge freedom of speech
thereof I find it uh discomforting that
somebody thinks that it is appropriate
to put their viewpoints on the entirety
of a city I am not a Christian and I do
not want this community to be run by
Christian laws I want this community to
be run by those laws which are
established by the elected officials as
chosen by those voters who come here and
have desires to live free and not be
subject to those restrictions which
people may choose to do personally uh he
is as an adult can do what he is free to
do luckily under our Bill of Rights both
the state federal and local level um but
when an individual begins to purport
that their morality should be imposed
upon others they have gone outside the
bounds upon which our very country was
founded as a 24-year military veteran
and a retired military disabled officer
uh I spent a significant amount of my
time uh under the opes of enforcing
protecting and providing those freedoms
to everyone irrespective of their
religion irrespective of their personal
views irrespective of whether I agree
with any of those or not the difficult
aspect of freedom of religion freedom of
speech and the other freedoms that are
provided under our bill of right and our
other governing documents of our nation
is that you will not agree with them all
the time there are many things that
people do with which I do not agree in
provided that they do not impinge upon
my rights nor breach any law established
at the city state or federal level the
unfortunate reality or in my instance as
I view it the fortunate reality is that
I have to let them do it that's supposed
to be the strength upon which our
country was founded thank you thank
you do we have any other speakers this
evening hi good evening my name is Patty
wome I live at 512 West Wheeling Street
here in Lancaster um I I wanted to let
you know that I am a longtime resident
of Lancaster um I was born and raised
here and moved away for a short time
time and moved back to Lancaster because
of the moral values and the family
values that we had here as a community
it's always been a safe place to be and
it's always been a good and wholesome
place to raise children and have a
family that we've got a lot of churches
here a lot of Christians in our
community and I have always been part of
that Christian
Community um I am here to address the
drag show that is scheduled on September
13th and September 14th um I I really
take offense to the September 14th
outside um in the Square just because
it's a personal it is a personal value I
will admit but it does go against the
city ordinance we talked about so if you
have heard previously according to city
ordinance
11391 sexually oriented less is
prohibited from being promoted and the
drag show is a blatant example of
that we are a Christian Community the
majority of us want to live in a
community that promotes Family Family
Values in a Godly environment to live in
peace and safety we don't want the
division that that can cause when you
bring those other elements into our town
because we don't have drag people here
they generally come in from a larger
Community like Columbus I don't believe
that a drag show in the heart of
downtown Lancaster fits with our
community
standards I believe that the Bible is
the revealed word and will of God and it
is our book for living it is our
Commandments for living and according to
Romans chapter 1 God call this Behavior
vile among many other things the
promotion of sexually oriented
businesses has been proven to cause
moral Decay and ruin in many great
cities across our nation if you look at
the cities even Columbus if you've been
Downtown Columbus anytime recently and
you go to the short North where a lot of
this started it's just the helpful
excuse my French it's just a terrible
place to be it's just
horrible today in my neighborhood my
neighbor one of my neigh neighbors told
me that she and her sister often would
frequent downtown Lancaster they both
are married both have three little
children each and they will no longer go
to LC Cafe for coffee where they used to
go and take their children because they
found out that one of the owners is a
registered tier 2 sex offender which
means he has been found with and
convicted of child pornography and they
don't think that that fits in with the
standards in their in our community so
they will no longer take their children
there because they do not want to have
them exposed to that kind of behavior
and um I too use the same quote from
Edmund BKE the only thing necessary for
the Triumph of e evil is for good men to
do nothing because for most of you I
don't know most of you don't I know
Becky but I am not a public speaker I
rarely get involved in these kind of
things but to me this is a real
heartfelt issue it's something that's
not easy for me to do to stand up in
front of here and speak my commitment
which is it is is a very longtime
Christian commitment so as a member of
the newly formed Fairfield Family Forum
our motto being standing firm to protect
traditional Family Values I'm asking you
to enforce our city ordinance ma'am
you've reached your three minute limit
to stop the plan drag show and any
further planned drag shows in the future
so I appreciate you taking the time to
listen to me and to under to read
through the information that we had so
anyway thank you so much thank you
hello everyone my name is Addison Curry
and I live at 4765 fosma school Road
Southwest I'm 19 years old and currently
a sophomore at Ohio University I'm here
today to speak about my personal
experience on the emerging radical
gender ideology that has been
infiltrating our city from boys playing
on girls sports teams and using girls
locker rooms at the high school to grown
men asking to use the women's restroom
at our city pool I have experienced this
trend in real time and I couldn't be
more concerned I attended Lancaster High
School and graduated in 2023 I played
field hockey from my freshman to my
junior year in that time there was a boy
who presented him as a girl and played
on our team he would participate as if
he were a girl like the rest of us he
would ride the bus to games and enter
the girls locker rooms and change with
us this made most of us very
uncomfortable and nothing was ever said
to us about him being a boy although we
had our suspicions nothing was ever
mentioned to my parents either I imagine
that these instances will continue to
grow and be protected in the future
during my summer breaks for the past 4
years I've been a lifeguard for the
Lancaster City Pools for three of those
years at ages 17 18 and 19 I've been a
head guard it has been a wonderful time
that is until this past summer this past
summer we've had many many issues at the
pools the worst issue in memory was when
a very obvious man in a women's bathing
suit told us he was uncomfortable
entering the men's bathroom in that
moment we allowed him to enter the pool
through the guard room we have never had
this problem before and at one point he
requested to use the women's restroom we
were all Unsure how to proceed while we
were trying to figure out what to do he
chose to enter the men classroom we
elevated the concern to our supervisor
and eventually to our manager her
solution was to leave the decision up to
us the lifeguards this is not fair to do
to teenagers the only possible thing we
could come up with was to clear out the
bathrooms and that is a major
inconvenience to those who belong in
those bathroom when we told the man that
there were women in the women's bathroom
he and he would have to wait he ran into
the men's bathroom with no hesitation at
all the very next day the same man came
back to the pool and he did not even ask
us to check if there was anyone in the
women's bathroom he just instantly went
into the men's bathroom so this poses
the question if he truly felt
uncomfortable why would he enter the
men's locker room without any issue
especially after telling us it made him
extremely uncomfortable to go into the
men's bathroom from Boys on girls sports
teams to men wanting to use the women's
bathroom at the pool to the ongoing
display and support of Pride activities
downtown sponsored by organizations that
Target this messaging towards kids and
now drag B show I have to wonder what is
happening to Lancaster Ohio is this the
same town I grew up in when I'm ready to
start a family is this really want where
I want to settle down ladies and
gentlemen of city council these radical
ideologies have slowly infiltrated our
city but make no mistake they are here
and they are evolving and spreading you
must recognize the very real threat
these radical ideas pose to this town
and how unfavorable it is for young
family oriented adults like myself ma'am
you've reached your three minute limit
how can I feel safe to raise my children
here thank
you good evening my name is Jason Curry
I live at for 765 Falls all School Road
Southwest as you all heard my name's
Jason I am the abison Curry's
father I would like to speak from a
father's point of view and you can't
imagine how I felt when I learned that
this boy was playing on the same team
using the same bathrooms in the same
locker rooms as my
daughter I felt betrayed by the adults
that are entrusted to protect my little
girl I
felt
missed by the coaches and the Schools
administration who were
responsible whose responsibility was to
let us all know
my daughter would have never been on
that team had I had
know because it's not
okay for a biological man to be in the
same locker room as my
child
changing but not that she my child the
rest of the daughters on the
teeth as a father do I not have the
right to
know you it's absolute BS
and now because of the growing publicity
support and affir affirmation this
ideology is spreading and infiltrating
our communities beyond the
schools now I have to worry about my
daughter's being approached by a man
wanting to use the women's restroom in
their summer jobs at the pool my younger
daughter was also a lifeguard this year
she decided to step down from that role
because this made her so
uncomfortable and when they reached out
to their
manager their manager refuses still yet
to this day to answer emails about what
policy is being put in
place my wife wishes she could be here
to speak this evening with you all but
she had to work she graduated from
Lancaster High School along with
myself her picture is up in the halls of
Lancaster High School for for sports
achievements we have the history at this
school in the city inv vested interest
and to see success my wife has reached
out as a concerned mother and Patron of
the pools to no
answers she and I are absolutely
disgusted in in the direction of the
schools in this city which is why we
called which is why we decided to
homeschool my younger two kids this year
and will continue to homeschool my
younger two
kids you all have this information what
will you do with it what direction will
the city take thank you for your
time good evening my name is denell
couch I live at 4625 Jacobs Ladder Road
in Lancaster um I'm a mother of four I'm
a small business owner um and I've lived
in Fairfield County my whole life um I
was absolutely um a calleded and
dismayed over an event um that we
recently found out called light the
night um it is a drag show event and
glow
parade um I find that extremely
offensive um confusing to Children a
horrible influence on our society and
counter to the Faith and family values
that farful county has been founded upon
um for
Generations um I have a couple questions
just to open-ended questions um not for
you to respond but just for you to to
think about is number one um how did
they get permission to hold this kind of
lewd and obscene event in the Public
Square of Fairfield County downtown
Lancaster and number two how is it that
my taxpayer dollars are funding this
anti family event um through the Fai
County library and the fairi County
Health Department um New
Horizons
Etc thank you for your time have a great
evening good evening city council folks
uh mayor safety service director law
director um my name is Amanda Everett um
I live in the city limits at 2011 South
High Street here in Lancaster and as you
are all aware I also serve as the
Director of destination downtown
Lancaster uh I think that as someone who
has attended multiple Pride
events um there are so many families
there and not all families are like your
families and from an economic
development perspective it is unwise and
unloving to not be open welcoming and
affirming to All Families even if they
don't look like yours we have a
tremendous opportunity here to recruit
and retain young talent and create a
city that is welcoming and affirming
where everyone feels safe there are
multiple Christian events that are
hosted on an annual basis in the Public
Square for those folks that are not
Christian they can choose not to attend
they can scroll through on Facebook and
choose not to go to the Bible reading
because some people have experienced
serious trauma and sexual assault within
those Church settings but even with that
those facts and that data and those
personal deeply personal
stories many critically thinking
individuals know that that's not all
Christians and that's not all Christians
spaces and I'm going to get to know more
before I pass judgment and start
labeling things that they have not seen
before as lewd or disgusting or
pornographic when that is not in fact
the
case thank you for your time and thank
you for keeping
Lancaster a top city that is welcoming
safe and affirming for All Families even
if they don't look like yours
sir please refrain from making comments
in the audience if you wish to make a
comment please come to the podium and
identify yourself in your name and your
address speaking of good evening my name
is Eli schlake and I live at 763 L Rico
Boulevard in Lancaster
Ohio a lot of you know me and a lot of
uh people I recognize in this audience
I've gone to school with I serve at
Provisions or I have dealt with you in
the public capacity as I've been
volunteering around the
city to sit here and be told that you
know my existence and the existence of
my queer brothers and sisters who are
simply trying to get a paycheck is an
Abomination is something that is lewd is
something that is pornographic is simply
untrue the fact that we are here the
fact that we are putting on this event
to show our pride and the fact that we
are publicly doing so is not something
that is pornographic or lewd or vile it
is simply the fact that we exist and if
that is too much for you to deal with
then you may stay home that is all I
have to say I hope you all have a
wonderful
evening hi there I am Jerry comr 1565
Rosemont Court Northeast Lancaster Ohio
and being a lifelong musician I would
love to start break out in a song of
capital T that rhymes with P that stands
for pool and any of you that know that
joke or The Music Man understands
exactly what's going on this evening
because it's all about what's the big
villain what's going on um I've heard
people talk about morality and the
Lancaster they know and I'll tell you I
grew up in Lancaster and I live here and
I and I'll tell you the I know it is
full of wonderful
people and very caring people and gay
people and lesbian people and Christian
people and black people and Jewish
people and all kinds of people but when
some people try to say what is right and
what is wrong is when it comes into a
really big problem and they can hide
behind the Bible all they want the Bible
by the way also has a lot to say about
uh killing people and rape and and all
kinds of horrible things that God
condoned the Bible says lots of I would
never want to read this to Children
there's there's scary stuff in there but
people all the time say read the Bible
read the Bible I know the Bible
backwards and forwards I do and I know
goodness and Badness and there's all
kinds of things in there but don't stand
behind it and say this is right and this
is
wrong and this kind of event being
promoted is here's the whole reason it
exist
exists because to this day a man and a
woman can walk down any Street anywhere
and no one's going to yell things or
throw things at you or try to beat you
up when we still live in a society
that's simply holding someone's hand and
walking down the street hand in hand has
seen as pornographic or evil or awful
that's why Pride exists because some
people still judge and some people here
right now are showing you if you don't
want to come to this event don't come to
this event it's really that simple it's
so easy and when they say it's out in
the streets yes it is there's usually by
the way there's usually police there or
sheriffs and I think there's going to be
this time so if something lwd is going
on by all means arrest them it's that
simple it's that
simple because I believe there is Police
or Sheriff's going to be there so they
see lewdness by all means or something
pornographic again arrest them it's a
simple fix so don't go or if you want to
show up again police will be there in
protection but sometimes the sadness is
the police are there protecting the
people they're just trying to have a
nice time I worry for the safety of
those people I don't worry for any other
safety in those
moments and as far as people if if you
know a 14-year-old might happen upon
this occasion and be offended or what
okay where how did you not know your
14-year-old old was going to be there
the family should be monitoring this and
if they don't like it don't take them
it's really that simple it's that simple
we're trying to make it more complex
than it is don't go to the event or you
can come to the event and that's fine
but also mind your maners again police
will be there so um as far as you know
labeling this kind of behavior or
activity as Lew or whatever I've been
there for five years and I've never seen
anything pornographic or lewd and by the
way pornography is I Believe by the
Supreme Court of the United States of
America you know it when you see it so
they can't even Define it so think about
that for a
moment sir you've reached your three
minute L okay thank you very much thank
you good evening my name is my name is
Elizabeth Jeffers I am uh residing at
2151 West fa
Avenue um this is the first I've heard
of this meeting so I'm not prepared of
these wonderful speakers all these
speakers have prepared they have
wonderful words and insight and um
powerful conviction um I just want to
share my point the gentleman in the
floral needs a
hug as as anybody here who's upset uh it
is a very uh coma emotionally uh
Division and uh that to me is scary and
that can um build up
into drama
trauma um I do follow the Bible and I do
know that the Bible said God made
everyone and everyone is to be
loved um our society has determined what
that love is to mean I follow what Jesus
says and um it is not my position to
judge what someone else
does um and God gave us each a uh Free
Will and there is a lot of scary things
in the Bible and I wouldn't read every
bit of the Bible to an unsuspecting
child without
some further explanation of how the
situation came about in the Bible so the
Bible is good I don't want to use it to
beat somebody in the head with um but I
uh feel that my community I grew up in
and any Community I would be uh wanting
to live in would be um a safe
environment according to my
interpretation of what Jesus tells us
God shows as um sayfe that brings
religion into the situation I know you
guys
can't unnecessarily um use that as a
decision that you're making you're
making more of a political and
um secular decision I don't believe that
you're allowed to make scriptural
decisions on your board I just want to
uh express my opinion and um I think we
all need a hug we need understanding and
um it's not easy to do when we're up in
arms and I'm relying on the Holy Spirit
to give me the proper words
and God's love it's bigger than me I
might not be able to do it myself but
I'm relying on the Holy Spirit to give
me God's love towards people who don't
look like me or say talk like me or act
like
me
um I don't know if that helps your
decision or anything but I'm looking for
a decision towards uh an environment
that
is like in the 50s
there has been uh gay individuals since
the beginning of time ma'am you've
reached your three minute limit and
appreciate your time and
um I hope that everyone can walk away
with a positive God's love environment
thank
you okay ladies and gentlemen I don't
see anybody else making their way to the
podium okay I spoke too soon all right
there we go you Scot green 603 Crestview
Drive um the audience that thinks they
know the Bible you might actually want
to read it and open it once in a while
because you are
deceived uh for
councel um we're asking to follow the
laws that are currently on the books
we've been presented with those we ask
that you enforce those and do your job
um this Outline by the statutes that you
guys to to up hold um we expect you to
do that
uh we are not going to go away uh we
will be here and if needed we can
replace you it's not
hard it is if you aren't living in the
city of Lancaster which I don't believe
you do do you but I know people down
here and I have people that are already
willing to
run
okay so thank you
uh good evening city council my name is
Maxwell yanar I live at 1372 Rainbow
Drive Northwest and I would just like to
come up here and express uh what I've
viewed today um this is a very hostile
environment right now and I don't
believe that this is the place to be
hostile towards each other I get that
there are some you know differing views
and we don't all agree on everything but
I would just like to point out um one
gentleman I feel threat threaten by what
you have said with um saying that the
police would be there and ready to
arrest me and assuming that I or anyone
that does not agree with things that are
going on that the threat of police
activity towards me I feel threatened by
that first of all just my opinion but um
I'm a 19-year-old male I want to my
family's established here my dad is a
surgeon helps people no matter what you
look like no matter what you believe and
I believe the same thing but there is
one thing that I do disagree with drag
shows can be a show of Pride and who you
are but I feel like it's being forced
upon me but if that is being expected of
me to accept and then if I being a white
male with a
fiance I'm judged
I can't say it's normal to be a male in
a female relationship I can say it's
normal to be male male or female female
but there's an immediate prejudice
against me and I just would like
everyone to think about our political
status in this country it doesn't matter
if you're voting for red or blue I think
it should matter on the you know what
you think of people I think of people as
human beings nothing else doesn't matter
what you are doesn't matter what you do
you are a human being we have the same
DNA we're here to live doesn't matter if
it's for God or if it's for
yourself thank
you hi can you guys hear me thank you uh
my name is Matt denowitz I live at 306
North High Street here in Lancaster
excuse me um we just moved here maybe
about 3 months ago but went to high
school here so did my wife who lived
here a little bit longer before um there
are a lot of false equivalencies being
thrown around here I would ask you
dismiss those in your in your judgments
here sir I can't sir you're going to
need to speak a little bit louder into
the mic thank you thank you it do better
thank you uh there are a lot of false
equivalencies being thrown around here
uh I would ask that they be dismissed in
the Judgment here um I was raised in the
church I I still think my faith is a bit
of a mystery to me but um one thing that
I have learned along the way is that
God's love is always changing and our
interpretation of that is always
changing and I think that to open your
heart to that is to understand why women
can speak in the church and why the
Catholic church is even moving to you
know accept the homosexual Community the
lgbtq community um and I think that part
of that change is just natural you you
can't fight that um fighting that is
regressive and it's going to set us back
here part of the reason we move back to
Lancaster was for family but part of it
was also you drive through downtown and
you start to see a different town and
more cultur sir I still can hear you I
can't hear a word you're say understand
the thing you're saying is there a way
to turn up the
microphone no is there a way to turn up
the microphone off by accident no okay
slow down is the green light slow down
project yeah I can't understand you all
right when we move back to town better
yeah all right give me a thumbs up or
thumbs down if I go down thank you when
we move back to town it's because we
started to see the town that we want to
live in whole reason we left in the
first place was not a lot of diversity
not a lot of acceptance a very
predominant line of thinking um coming
back to this town we're proud to bring
our friends here proud to bring our
family here proud to show off what the
town is becoming proud to see that the
town is becoming a little more worldly
Lancaster does not need to be a closed
off Place Lancaster should open it heart
to the lgbtq community continue to do so
and so Drive Mutual acceptance on both
sides thanks thank
you
hello my name is Amy schl and I live at
763 L Rico Boulevard and I do vote for
city council so there you go um so my
family and when we talk about family
values my family includes drag so your
values I think it's already been stated
can be different but my family values
will include that so you have to kind of
keep that in mind and really this isn't
don't think a matter for you guys to
determine I think this is all a mute
point to bring this up and when we talk
about threat threat in that we're going
to replace
you that's kind of a threat um but yes
that's the that's the process that's the
Avenue if you want to replace city
council replace them um if you want to
keep them because they're doing a good
job then you keep them but to tell them
you know hey you're in charge of
admonishing this because it's wrong it's
not wrong it's simply not what you
prefer and that's your individual Choice
that's your free will God gave you that
free will everybody somebody said it yes
you have that Free Will and I remember
you know the golden rule was different
among many religions but one of them in
particular and I can't remember the
religion says that you know it's not do
unto others as others would do unto you
but it's that instead of there being God
that God exists within each and every
one of us and that's what you guys
really need to start to try to find
because you um we are addressing I'm
addressing them they can hear me it's
okay so I'm going to talk to my friends
out here in the community that you can
find God within each other and then then
you can practice that great command
which is love your command is to
love okay it's not a threat to mention
that there's going to be police there
that's a safety blanket for those that
have been persecuted and targeted simply
because of their
existence police is there if you think
it's lewd
please contact the police and have them
arrested they didn't say we're going to
have you arrested have the individual
that you believe is lewed and breaking
the ordinance of 1139 01 have them
arrested if you think it's obscene
please go to the police and have that
individual that's being obscene arrested
if you think it's deviant I'm not sure
if that's a law but yeah then go and
have them arrested if you think it's
pornograph traffic go to the police
that's not a threat that's encouraging
you to use the system that's available
to
you it's okay if they do it in private
that's the other thing it's okay if they
do it in
private but they're not allowed to be in
public because I live in the city limits
and I pay the city tax dollars and so
does my
son but that's not okay for him to be in
the square and utilize it for that
purpose I'm just again ma'am you've
reached your three minutes I thank you
thank
you can
I no we we've had comment from everybody
if you have an apology to make or
there's apology you wish to make reach
out to the individual during at the end
of the meeting apology to council I
didn't expect this to turn into this all
we was asking was for Council to review
existing ordinances
fly to enforce them we have nothing
against sir thank you for your comments
we're we're going to move on with the
business portion of the meeting um do we
have one more we we have one more
okay I'm Regina Shaw I live at 137 East
malberry Street um first I just want to
say my sister Amy was the one speaking
and so I'm going to try to finish some
of her thoughts but just more over that
there was a church that had an event um
this past weekend down at the square not
a church that I go to believe in not
that I have any alignment with and I
walked by and people were having a good
time and they seemed very happy there
and I was glad to see our Square meeting
the needs of our community that was one
small section of the community but they
got to use it I don't understand the
difference if the church can be down
there and they can have a fair for their
friends and families and open it to the
public why we can't have this event
what's really the difference because you
don't like it well I was raised Catholic
a little bit upset with the Catholic
Church they let sexual assault
happen vile things happen women are
disrespected every day so I left the
Catholic church I have friends who are
Catholic they still go to church I don't
stand out there and block them and tell
them they can't do it I don't come here
asking you to do that I'm just simply
saying
let them have their space and if you
don't like it don't be there that's all
thank you okay L we've we've reached the
end of public comment for this evening
and we'll be moving into the business
portion of the
meeting reports of standing committees
finance committee minutes dated August
26 2024 submitted by Mr
wolfinger Mr President I like to make a
motion to receive and file the reports
of standing committees second we have a
motion and second to receive and file
the reports of standing committees all
those in favor please say I I all those
opposed same sign we move to reports of
special committees there are no reports
or special committees present presented
to council this evening thank you public
hearings we have none this evening we'll
move on now to the reading of
resolutions we'll move to third reading
of resolutions beginning with temporary
resolution
8524 a resolution to appropriate from
the unencumbered balance and to amend
the certificate Appropriations with the
county auditor in the general fund 10001
to fund the city's annual contribution
to the fairfi County Dog Shelter finance
committee Mr wolfinger and Mr alss
council member
wolfinger can um I make a motion I'm
sorry I thought it was going to be
tabled I'm sorry well if I didn't know
it goes to the sponsor first okay and he
can make a motion so okay thank you uh
Mr President I would like to make a
motion to council pass and gross and
enter on the written record uh
resolution temporary number
8524 second we have a motion and second
to pass Andross and enter upon the
written record temporary resolution
discussion um
this motion is
to U fund the city's portion owed to the
fearo county do sh any further
discussion council member ke yes um uh
Stephanie I'm going to refer to you can
I at table after he's already done that
or is
that that's a good question that I'm
Googling right now so give me just a
second uh to review Robert's Rules of
Order would it be a motion to amend out
of curiosity no okay no
motion already made the motion to
approve and a second so now we have to
we have to vote if we want to table it
we have to vote s turns into a
nightmare it's a nightmare that's why I
thought
you recall the vote of the next meeting
yes
on we can bring it up
again so we have a motion in a second
can we move forward law
direct I I wish say call for question
but that's
Rob that's not debatable yep no um the
president recognized um councilman
wolfinger first so the chair already
recognized him and we have a motion in a
second and we need to vote now okay so
we will move to call the
Ro sorry I was expecting to tap that one
okay m aers yes yes aers she's saying my
name first I don't know okay it's just
I'm just trying to play
along all right let me start over Mr
aers yes Mr alss yes Mr bjack yes Mrs
hoop yes Mr lenberg yes Mr
niser I'm Sorry Miss KES yes Mr skover
yes Miss tener no
Mr Wing yes and Mr wolfanger
yes temporary resolution
8524 passes 9 to one we'll now move on
to Temporary resolution
8624 a resolution authorize the service
safety director to advertise for bids
and enter into a contract for
construction on of the booving Road
South Broad Street and hurg Road
Improvement program Paving project um
Public Works and Miss Tiner and Mr
lerberg council member tener Mr uh
president i' would like to make a motion
to pass and gross and enter upon the
written record temporary resolution
8624 second we have a motion and second
pass and gross and enter upon the
written record temporary resolution
8624 a discussion council member team
yes this is just uh what it says is to
advertise for bids for booving Road
South uh Broad Street and Hamburg Road
any further discussion hearing none
please call it all Mr aers yes Mr ALS
yes Mr bisj yes Mrs Kates yes Mrs hoop
yes Mr lenberg yes Mr skover yes Miss
tener yes Mr Wing yes and Mr wolfinger
yes temporary resolution
8624 passes 10 to0 temporary resolution
8724 a resolution to authorize the
service safety director to apply for a a
grant through the Ohio Public Works
commission to fund the Arbor Valley
Drive Rehabilitation project um is
through Public Works M Miss tener and M
K council member tener Mr President I'd
like to make a motion to council pass
and gross and enter upon the written
record temporary resolution 8724 second
we have a motion second to pass Andross
enter upon the written record temporary
resolution
8724 any discussion council member yes
this is the prif for Grant uh regarding
Arbor valy drive that's at the high
school from uh what 37 down any further
discussion hearing none please call the
role Mr aers yes Mr alss yes Mr bisj yes
Mrs KES yes Mrs hoop yes Mr lenberg yes
Mr skover yes Miss tener yes Mr Wing yes
and Mr wolfinger yes temporary
resolution 8724 passes 10 to Z temporary
resolution 88 24 a resolution to
authorize the service safety director to
enter into a Design preconstruction
Services contract with various
consultants for the East Main Street
Improvement project PID
122006 to appropriate from the UN
incomer balance and to amend the
certificate of Appropriations with the
county otter and the general fund
10001 this is through um Public Works um
Mrs Miss Tiner and Mr lenberg council
member ten Mr President I'd like to make
a motion the council pass and gross and
enter upon the written record temporary
resolution
8824 second we have a motion and second
to pass and gross and enter upon the
written record temporary resolution 8824
council member tener discuss this just
get contracts in that to move forward
with the East Main Street
project any further discussion hearing
none please call the r Mr aers yes Mr
alses yes Mr bisj yes Mrs crit yes Mrs
hoop yes Mr lenberg yes Mr skover yes
Miss tener yes Mr Wing yes Mr wolfinger
yes temporary resolution 8824 passes 10
to Zer temporary resolution
8924 a resolution to authorize the
service safety director to enter into an
engineering agreement for construction
Administration and inspection services
for the East Main Street sewer
separation and an Court drainage
improvements phase project phase one
project uh through water water pollution
Mr Wing and Mr alss council member Wing
uh thank you Mr President I'd like to
make a motion that Council pass and gr
and enter upon the WR record temporary
resolution number 89- 24 second we have
a motion second to pass and gross and
enter upon the written record temporary
resolution
8924 discussion council member Wing yes
thank you Mr President uh we've
discussed this project at length so I
won't go into too much detail but just a
reminder this piece is to enter into um
construction Engineering Services and
the next pieces to go out to bid thank
you any further discussion hearing none
please call the RO Mr alers yes Mr ALS
Mr bisj yes Mrs KES Mrs hoop yes Mr
lenberg yes Mr skover yes Miss tener yes
Mr Wing yes Mr wolfinger yes temporary
resolution
8924 passes 10 to zero temporary
9024 a resolution authorize the service
safety director to advertise for bids
and enter into a contract to construct
the East Main Street sewer separation
and in court drainage improvements phase
one project um water water pollution Mr
Wing and Miss tener council member Wing
uh thank you Mr President I'd like to
make a motion that Council pass Andross
and enter upon the written record
resolution temporar number 90-24 second
we have a motion and second to pass and
gross and enter upon the written record
temporary resolution 9024
any discussion council member Wing
nothing further hearing no further
discussion please call a roll Mr alers
yes Mr ALS yes Mr bisack yes Mrs crates
yes Mrs hoop yes Mr lenberg yes Mr
skover yes M Tiner yes Mr Wing yes Mr
wolfinger yes temporary resolution 9024
passes 10 to zero temporary resolution
9124 a resolution to increase receipts
in fund 805 8 Violet Township of
Lancaster Jed uh amend the certificate
of other sources with the county auditor
and appropriate from the UN incomer
balance and Amed the certificate of
Appropriations with the county auditor
in the violent Township city of
Lancaster Jed fund 8058 and income tax
fund
2016 Finance um Mr wolfinger Mr aers
council member wolfinger yes Mr
President I'd like to make a motion that
Council pass and gross and interal and
written record to temporary resolution
number 91 d24 second we have a motion a
second to pass and gross enter upon the
written record temporary resolution
9124 discussion council member wolfinger
yes uh this is merely adjusting the
revenue uh for the ched that's uh been
created in Violet Township any further
discussion hearing none please call a r
Mr aers yes Mr alses yes Mr bisj yes
Miss Mrs cres yes Mrs hoop yes Mr
lenberg yes Mr skover yes Miss tener yes
Mr Wing yes Mr wolfinger yes temporary
resolution 9124 passes 10 to Zer
temporary resolution
9224 a resolution to authorize the city
of Lancaster to apply for a.gov domain M
migration Grant a cyber security
software and services Grant to execute
contracts as required administrative
services Mr lenberg and Mr
bisack Mr
lenberg yes thank you Mr President I
would like to make a motion that Council
pass Andross and enter upon the written
record resolution temporarily number
9224 second we have a motion and second
to pass Andress enter upon the written
record temporary resolution
9224 any further discussion nothing at
this time it's pretty clearly written
thank
you please call the RO Mr aers yes Mr a
yes Mr bisj yes Mrs CR yes Mrs hoop yes
Mr lenberg yes Mr skover yes M tener yes
Mr Wing yes and Mr wolfinger yes
temporary resolution 9224 passes 10 to
zero temporary resolution
9324 a resolution to authorize
dispensing with competitive bidding for
the purchase of Regents for the au480
drug testing annual an annualy
analy analyzer at the Municipal Court
due to a soul Source provider um this is
law with Mrs Kites and Mr wolfinger
council member Crites yes thank you Mr
President I'd like to make a motion that
Council pass Andross and enter upon the
written record resolution temporarily
numbered
9324 second I have a motion and second
to pass Andress and enter upon the
written record temporary resolution 9324
any discuss discussion council member
Crites yes just as a reminder this is to
approve a purchase uh related to the mun
Court Municipal Court's drug testing
equipment with a single Source provider
in the amount of
$168,000 which has already been included
as part of the 2024 budget it is a
critical resource for the court as well
as other agencies which rely upon the
court for their drug testing thank you
any further discussion hearing none
please call the RO Mr aers yes Mr ALS
yes Mr bisj yes Mrs crates yes Mrs hoop
yes Mr L lenberg yes Mr skover yes Miss
tener yes Mr Wing yes Mr W figer yes
temporary resolution 9324 passes 10 to Z
we'll now move on to Second reading of
resolutions beginning with temporary
resolution
9624 a resolution to amend their
certificate of other sources in
Appropriations increase receipts and
appropriate from the UN incomer balance
in the police and fire Levy fund
2047 um Safety Committee and Mr bisj and
Miss tener council member bisj thank you
Mr President this is the second of three
readings second of three readings on
temporary resolution
9624 temporary resolution
9724 star a resolution to authorize the
service safety director to enter into a
contract for construction of the Tiki
Lane booster station Improvement project
um water water pollution Mr Wing Mr alss
council member Wing thank you Mr
President I'd like to make a motion
uh to replace resolution temporary
number
9724 with uh resolution temporary number
9724 star second have a motion in second
to replace temporary resolution
9724 with temporary resolution 9724 star
uh discussion council member Wing yes
thank you Mr President this is actually
just a a very quick and easy fix uh the
city had to push back the opening for
bids on this project by a week from
August 23rd August 30th so this version
of the this version of the legislation
uh reflects that change thank you any
further discussion on the motion to
replace hearing none please call the
rooll Mr aers yes Mr Al yes Mr bisj yes
Mrs Craig yes Mrs hoop yes Mr lenberg
yes Mr skover yes Miss tener yes Mr Wing
yes Mr wolfinger yes motion to replace
uh temporary resolution 9724 with
temporary resolution 972 24 star passes
10 to zero council member
Wing thank you Mr President I'd like to
make a motion that Council suspend its
rules and wave the third reading of uh
resolution temporary number 9724 start
second we have a motion and second to
suspend the rules and wave the third
reading of temporary resolution 9724
star any discussion yeah just as we've
discussed previously this is the the
last arpa project for my committee and
we have a a deadline to obtain those
funds thank you any further discussion
hearing none please call the roll on the
motion to
suspend Mr aers yes Mr ALS yes Mr
bizjack yes Mrs KES yes Mrs hoop yes Mr
lenberg yes Mr skover yes Miss tener yes
Mr Wing yes Mr wolfinger yes motion to
suspend the rules and wave the third
reading of temporary resolution 9724
star passes 10 to Zer uh council member
wing
thank you Mr President I'd like to make
a motion that Council pass engross and
enter upon the written record uh
resolution temporarily numbered 9724
star second a motion a second to pass gr
enter upon the written record temporary
resolution 9724 Star had a lot of
discussion do we need any more so I have
nothing further to add okay thank you
please call the rooll Mr alers yes Mr
alss yes Mr bisj yes Mrs kites yes Mrs
hoop yes Mr lenberg yes Mr skover yes
Miss tener yes Mr Wing yes Mr wolfinger
yes temporary resolution 9724 star
passes 10 to Zer temporary resolution
9824 a resolution authorize the service
safety director to enter into a contract
for construction of the southwater
plant concentrate booster pumps project
water water pollution and Mr Wing and
Miss tener council member Wing this will
be the second of three readings second
of three readings on temporary
resolution
9824 temporary resolution
99- 24 star a resolution appropriate
from the unencumber balance in the
engineering fund 1
190 for additional and amend the
certificate of Appropriations for the
county auditor and the general fund
10001 for the unexpected cost related to
Staffing changes in the addition of an
administrative assistant position in the
Engineering Department administrative
Services Mr lenberg and Mr wolfinger
council member lenberg yes Mr President
I would like to make a motion to replace
resolution temporarily numbered
9-24 uh with resolution temporarily
numbered 9924
star uh as given to the clerk in writing
prior to tonight's meeting second thank
you we have a motion in second to
replace for resolution 9924 star or 9924
with 9924 star as provided to the clerk
in writing prior to tonight's meeting um
any discussion yes apparently we
neglected to amend the certificate
Appropriations with the county auditor
in this piece the names of the expense
accounts were different than those
originally provided so those Corrections
have been made and this is the second of
two readings for this piece okay so um
so you'll be doing doing a motion to
suspend after I will be yes okay thank
you all right um please call the rooll
on the motion to replace Mr aers yes Mr
ALS yes Mr bisj yes Mrs KES yes Mrs hoop
yes Mr lenberg yes Mr skover yes Miss
tener yes Mr Wing yes Mr wolfanger yes
motion to replace temporary resolution
9924 with 9924 star passes 10 to zero
council member lenberg yes Mr President
I'd like to make a motion that Council
suspend its through rules and wave the
third reading of resolution temporarily
numbered
star second I have a motion a second to
suspend the rules and wave the third
reading temporary resolution 9924 star
any further discussion nothing at this
time thank you please call the roll on
the motion to suspend Mr alers yes Mr
ALS yes Mr bisj yes Mrs CR yes Mrs hoop
yes Mr lenberg yes Mr skover yes Miss
tener yes Mr Wing yes Mr wolfinger yes
motion to suspend the rules and wave the
third reading of temporary resolution
9924 star passes 10 to zero council
member lenberg yes Mr President I'd like
to make a motion that Council pass
Andross enter upon the written record
resolution temporarily numbered
9924 star second you have a motion the
second to pass and gross enter upon the
written record temporary resolution 9924
star any further discussion not at this
time he hearing none please call the RO
Mr alers yes Mr alss yes Mr bisj yes Mrs
K yes Mrs hoop yes Mr lenberg yes Mr
skover yes Miss tener yes Mr Wing yes Mr
wolfinger yes motion to pass and gross
and enter upon the written record
temporary resolution 24 star passes 10
to zero we have no first reading of
resolutions which is a first so we'll go
with that win we'll now move move on to
the reading of ordinances beginning with
temporary ordinance
2724 an ordinance to accept the final
plat for the Timber Top subdivision code
and Zoning Mr aers and Mrs
hoop council member aers thank you Mr
President I'd like to make a motion that
Council pass and gross and enter upon
the written record temporary ordinance
2724 second we have a motion and a
second to pass Andress and enter upon
the written record temporary ordinance
2724 any disc council member alens just
like the title says we're approving the
final plot and hopefully we can get work
going and finish that up over there so
that's all thank you any further
discussion hearing none please call the
RO Mr aers yes Mr alss yes Mr bisj yes
Mrs CR yes Mrs hoop yes Mr lenberg yes
Mr skover yes Miss tener yes Mr Wing yes
Mr wolfinger yes temporary ordinance
2724 passes 10 to Z move on to Second
reading of ordinance is beginning with
temporary ordinance
2824 an ordinance to amend permanent
ordinance
33-23 the non-union pay ordinance
administrative Services Mr lenberg and
Mr bisj council member lenberg uh yes Mr
President I'd like to make a motion that
Council suspend its rules and wave the
third reading of ordinance temporarily
numbered
2824 second we have a motion a second to
suspend the rule rules and wave the
third reading of temporary ordinance
2824 any discussion yes this uh came up
up at our last meeting
uh the administrative assistant to the
engineering department is retiring in
January and they would simply like to
hire someone in advance to get them up
to speed to uh replace the assistant any
further discussion on the motion to
suspend hearing none please call the
role Mr aers yes Mr ALS Mr bisj Mrs C
Mrs hoop yes Mr lenberg yes Mr skover
yes Miss tener yes Mr Wing yes Mr
wolfinger yes motion to suspend the
rules and wave the third reading of
temporary ordinance 2824 passes 10 to
zero council member lenberg yes Mr
President I'd like to make a motion that
Council pass and gross and enter upon
the written record ordinance temporarily
number 2824 second a motion is second to
pass and gross and enter upon the
written record temporary ordinance
2824 um any further discussion not at
this time hearing none please call a r
Mr aers yes Mr ALS yes Mr bjack yes Mrs
kites yes Mrs soup yes Mr lenberg yes Mr
skover yes Miss tener yes Mr Wing yes
and Mr wolfinger yes motion to pass uh
temporary ordinance 2824 passes 10 to
zero we'll now move on and this is quite
a bit of a read it looks like temporary
ordinance
3024 let me W my whistle an
ordinance um authorizing the city of
lancast Lancaster Ohio the city to enter
into an amendment to a natural grass gas
supply agreement a tax cert certificate
or tax
regulatory agreement a bond purchase
agreement and a continuing disclosure
agreement or commitment all is NE
necessary and any and all other
agreements that may be deemed necessary
or appropriate the agreements to
authorizing the use of certain financial
and demographic information of the city
in a preliminary official statement and
an official statement and continuing
disclosure in connection with the
issuance of revenue bonds by the
Lancaster Port Authority and through
three authorizing the payment of all
necessary Professional Services related
to the agreements the preliminary
official statement and the official
statement all for the purpose of the
purchase and distribution of natural gas
by the city and related to the issuance
of revenue bonds by the Lancaster Port
Authority to assist the city with its
acquisition of a supply of natural gas
including additional volumes for City
for sale to the city
and to declare an emergency finance
committee Mr wolfinger Mr ALS council
member wolfinger I am so tempted to
suspend that third
reading I'll get it by the third one
second reading second two second do that
second of three readings on temporary
ordinance I forgot even the name now
temporary ordinance
3024 all right thank you everyone uh
temporary ordinance 3124 an ordinance to
authorize the service safety director to
dispense with competitive bidding and
enter into a contract with the fairf for
County Board of Commissioners for Tyler
Technologies dispatching and Records
management software for the Lancaster
Police and Fire Departments to authorize
a then and now certificate for those
services and to declare an
emergency oh coming out of safety and Mr
bisj Miss tener council member bisj Jack
thank you Mr President I move that
Council suspend its rules and wave the
third reading for ordinance temporarily
number 3124 second we have a motion
second to suspend the rules and wave the
third reading of temporary ordinance
3124 council member ISJ I have nothing
at this time Mr President thank you any
further discussion hearing none please
call the rooll Mr alers yes Mr Al yes Mr
bisj yes Mrs cres yes Mrs hoop yes Mr
lenberg yes Mr skover yes Miss tener yes
Mr Wing yes and Mr wolfinger yes motion
to suspend the rules and wave the third
reading of temporary ordinance 3124
passes 10 to Z council member bisj thank
you Mr President I move that Council
pass and gross and enter upon the
written record ordinance temporarily
number
31-24 oh second a motion the second to
pass and gross and enter upon the record
temporary ordinance
3124 any discussion council member B uh
thank you Mr President as you all recall
last month we had quite a robust
conversation surrounding the piece of
legislation in short this legislation
allows the city to pick up its share of
the expense for the new dispatching
system that the county has graciously
allowed us to enter into a partnership
with thank you council member bisj any
further
discussion hearing none please call a r
Mr aers yes Mr ALS yes Mr bisj yes Mrs K
yes Mrs hoop yes Mr lenberg yes Mr
skover yes Miss tener yes Mr Wing yes
and Mr wolfinger yes temperate or
ordinance 3124 passes 10 to0 now move on
to the first reading of ordinances with
temporary ordinance
3224 an ordinance to accept the
annexation of 5.0 plus or minus acres in
Pleasant Township and to declare an
emergency um this is city council as a
whole and Mr skover and Miss tener
council member SC over Mr President i'
like to make a motion that Council
suspend its rules in W of the second and
third reading of temporary ordinance
3224 second we have a motion and second
to suspend the rules in way of the
second and third reading of temporary
ordinance
3224 any
discussion uh not at this time thank you
any further
discussion please call the rooll Mr
alers yes Mr ALS Mr bis yes Mrs CH yes
Mrs hoop yes Mr lenberg yes Mr skover
yes Miss tener yes Mr Wing yes and Mr
wolfinger yes motion to suspend the
rules in W of the second and third
reading of 3224 passes 10 to Z council
member scon over Mr President I'd like
to make a motion that Council pass and
gross enter upon the written record
temporary ordinance 3224 second we have
a motion second to pass and gross and
enter upon the written record temporary
ordinance 3224 any further discussion uh
just as a reminder this is the last
piece of the annexation of the last five
acres on Sheridan Drive
to finish off the well
the first part of development in that
section of town thank you any further
discussion hearing none please call our
Ro Mr aers yes Mr ALS yes Mr bisj yes
Mrs kites yes Mrs hoop yes Mr lenberg
yes Mr skover yes Miss tener yes Mr Wing
yes Mr wolfinger
yes motion to to pass uh temporary
ordinance 3224 passes 10 to zero
temporary ordinance
3324 and ordinance to authorize the
mayor to acquire five permanent drainage
easements necessary for the E East Main
Street sewer separation and and Court
drainage improvements phase one project
coming out of water water pollution Mr
Wing and Mr alss council member Wing uh
first of three readings please first of
three readings on temporary ordinance
3324 that concludes the reading of
ordinances this evening we'll now move
on to tabled legislation there being
none
um we now have unfinished business is
there any unfinished business from any
of the council members this evening
there are no unfinish business before
the council this evening well I'm I'm
asking them if they have anything that
they wish thank you oh wait a
minute she's like I want to go I want to
go council member
alers I I just want to address our
public comments earlier today um so I
have I just want to start by saying I
have full confidence and our law
director um to interpret our codes our
police force to enforce those codes and
our law committee to review and update
and modernize all of our codes um you
know as a openly bisexual member of the
city council I struggle to hear some of
what we had to listen tonight about you
know certain aspects of people's lives
being
Abominations um unfortunately as we saw
and we will always see people don't care
what you do how friendly you are how
conservative how traditional how liberal
how Progressive you are they'll always
have an issue with you no matter how
much they agree with you just based off
one little thing um and so in saying you
know I will be going to that drag show
this weekend it'll be a fun time um and
you know it is a paid event to get in
you're this is not something random
people are walking off into off the
street unless they want to pay and give
to um so you know I fully support
updating modernizing all our codes in
this aspect and the enforcement of them
as they should be but I I cannot sit
here and listen to people stand in uh
belittle members of our community based
off of something they were born with and
that as sexual orientation I just simply
cannot stand for that that's all thank
you council member aers um is there any
other council member Tina I do have a
question to ask Stephanie um I mean it's
been it's it's an enclosed event correct
by enclosed you mean indoors it's
indoors there's only so many tickets per
fire code correct yes whenever and over
yes that's correct whenever the
establishment received their occupancy
permit the fire department would have
given them a number that they could not
exceed and I'm sure they're aware of
that it's it's typically posted
prominently someplace yes and it is my
understanding that is an 18 and over
event well I I will say last year I
walked my dog downtown and last year an
Amanda ever can tell you I I was walking
my dog downtown I saw all this glowing
stuff I'm thinking oh you know and I am
a single um uh heterosexual female but I
was going downtown with my dog and I saw
all this glowing stuff and I'm going and
I'm like oh this looks fun and then
somebody's like oh this is a gay event
I'm like oh my gosh I'm on City councel
everybody's gonna think Becky Tina's a
lesbian here because she's here with her
her dog and I mean I was like but you
know I honestly did not see anything
there was a lot of glowing stuff there
was thing and I honestly you know I I
mean I have
friends that do the lifestyle and uh I
don't say oh they're my gay friend
they're my transgender friends they're
just my friends I don't I don't label
them like you know and I I mean I don't
know I grew up with and I know most of
you in this room grew up with Flip
Wilson doing Geraldine you grew up with
uh Monty Python you grew up with Benny
Hill you grew grew up with all these
different things and I know my brother
and
sister-in-law um he's retired Columbus
Police Officer and you know I'm not
going to tell you how many times he's
been married he likes women but
um anyway he they go to this drag show
he lives in Megs County they have the
drag shows there and I'm telling you
what there's no lewd things going on I
do believe some things are they do have
lewd things going on but I I do think
that the police would shut it down uh I
think a lot of people are still going
after what happened a few years back
with JD Henderson I think that is still
in people's mind I don't think that was
handled right but I think people still
have that in their minds and um I just I
just don't know I mean I'm not going I
have no reason to go I I just you know I
just don't go and uh I remember back in
the day how many of you women went to
the uh what were those shows with the
guy stripping what were those guys I
can't remember what they were called you
know your marriage you're going to that
what
Chippendales okay I mean I'm just saying
thank you for the well it was at Valley
day I remember it but anyway but I'm
just saying just because you don't agree
with it which I don't live that
lifestyle but I'm just telling you over
the weekend I spoke with somebody and
and and she said to me and I love her to
death but she goes oh they show their
git tell you and I said have you ever
seen them show their git tell you well
know but that's what I heard and I think
too many people are feeding off of each
other of what's going on I have brought
my yearbook which is fun and I looked
through it because I remembered this
back in
1980 we had a powderpuff soft uh
football game we were all dressed up
like boys in our you know the football
attire the guys and I have a picture to
show one of the guys had a bikini top on
with stars on it and all of our parents
came and that and I mean it's it's how
you're raising your kids you know pay
attention to your kids and for somebody
that made a comment about you know
replacing
us we'll go ahead replace this because I
know somebody in this
uh Gallery tonight has a court date
coming up for something they did so for
you to point fingers at people I think
you need to point them back at
yourself right thank you council member
tener um I would take this opportunity
to provide this comment our meetings are
public meetings it is a Public Square
essentially we have a valid uh way that
people can come and make comment they
get three minutes um we have a process I
would encourage everybody yes come make
comments but be respectful we're all
neighbors we are all people here who
live in this community um I gave me a
little bit of a pause when somebody said
they felt unsafe about you know hearing
some of the comments ments made that is
not what this is for and we will I will
guarantee maintain theorum in this
meeting we will not have people talking
over each other we will not have people
um directing comments at each other you
are here to address Council and we will
welcome your comments and we appreciate
them so just wanted to make that clear
for everybody does anybody else have any
unfinished business council member
schoonover
um I just I wanted
to there's a lot to unpack when you know
I think when people sit in the audience
and listen to us go through legislation
and they're like man they're just
speeding through that and it's a bunch
of yes votes and whatever we've had
weeks and weeks to digest what we're
going through and then when we have a
situation like this with a lot of public
comment I think the misconception is we
don't listen to or care what you're
saying or what you're speaking about but
it's it's just there's a lot to unravel
so I won't go into everything I'm
sitting here as we're trying to go
through the meeting looking at various
codes for certain things that people
brought up and dealing with some of
those law enforcement codes and dealing
with the law director's office in my in
my full-time job that there's a lot of
interpret ation there I think that has
to be unpacked but I do want to address
the the swimming
pool situation because I think we're
we're going to see more of those
situations and I think that we have to
you know when we're talking about what
can council do what council can't do I
mean I I I think the the drag show
situation inside a private business I
don't know how much we can do with that
even if we wanted to now I don't know
anything about it being in the Square
okay but when we're talking about our
city pools things like
that we just need to be Forward Thinking
in terms of those policies and
situations that might come up I don't
agree with what happened I'm not a fan
of that when you're put on the spot in
that situation I I don't know that's a
that's a tough spot for teenagers young
adults trying to figure that out because
you don't know who's being genuine in
that
situation are they they legitimately
feel that way they or are they a
pedophile trying to take advantage so
that I think is a situation where we can
have more discussion and we've had
discussion um with the administration so
those things
are something that I feel when you bring
it to council we are having those
conversations as far as the drag show
and things like that regardless of your
opinion on it it doesn't mean that we
can do anything about it we can sit and
listen and obviously we can ask
questions but it's very hard for us to
turn around while we're doing everything
else and try and address those things so
I think speaking I apologize speaking
for everyone around the room it's it's
hard to sit up here and respond to you
it's that in the
same time frame of you know cuz then
it's just a back and forth thing so I
was not doing anything except looking up
codes on my phone when I was sitting
here when we're trying to do other
business and I just think it's one of
those things where there's a lot of in
my seven years here there's a lot of
misconception on what city council can
do can't do does do do we get read in on
when trees are being taken
down no you know that you know do we
deal with it after the fact absolutely
do we get read in on on policies and
procedures maybe not necessarily
initially but you know when certain
things and again I referen the pool
situation I would have never thought to
have a policy in place before that
happened so in a situation like that
we're going to have to react to it and
it's I think our responsibility to make
sure we're all acting appropriately
about that and if that doesn't happen
then that's a conversation we have to
have so sorry for the long- winded
response but there's a ton to unpack in
those comments thank you thank you
council member skover anybody else and
unfinished council member ker I do
respect what was done that day at the
pool I don't I mean I think that was a
good decision because you didn't know
and I thought that was a good decision
for that day but I do not think boys
should be using girls restrooms I don't
think girls should be using boys
restroom and boys shouldn't be playing
girl Sports and but I really respect
with you guys the decision that day but
there's absolutely no reason for a man
you just can't change that as much as
you want that's just my opinion you need
to stay where you're in your own lane
thank you for your comments um any
further comments from Council
Members okay we're going to conclude on
finish business new business any new
business hearing none we'll move to
announce of scheduled
meetings
um next regular sessions of council
September 23rd at 6:30 p.m. and there's
a in Focus presentation by the city
planner October 14th at 6:30
p.m. special meetings special meetings
um special Council meetings Saturday for
September 14th at 9:00 a.m. City Hall
1897 coner conference room and that
special meeting will be Council training
on budget and the budgeting process and
somebody's arching her eyebrows because
she's maybe not um and also doing some
strategic planning uh regularly
scheduled committee meetings um number
one uh administrative Services September
18th at 8:00 a.m. City Hall 1897
conference room Finance September 23rd
at 6: p.m. uh council
chambers uh water water pollution
committee September 27th at 7:30 a.m.
City Hall 1897 conference room Safety
Committee October 4th at 8:00 a.m. City
Hall 1897 conference room reading of
bills um M mnco
$16.85 public publication of
legislation Mr President I like to make
a motion to pay the bills second a
motion second to pay the bills all those
in favor please say I I
oppose same sign thank you there's no
need for an executive session at this
time I would entertain a motion to
adjourn Mr President I would like to
make that motion we adjourn second have
motion second adjourn all those in favor
please say I I I we're adjourned thank
you please remember council members to
sign your legislation before you leave
this
evening saf
[Music]
hi this is Chuck Sims with the Lancaster
dare program dare provides students with
skills to resist the pressure of drugs
gangs and violence and emphasizes
self-esteem good decision- making and
communication skills this month when you
buy a car truck or SUV from Buckeye
Toyota or Buckeye Honda the Buckeye
cares program will make a generous
donation to DARE with every vehicle they
sell thanks Buckeye for your continued
support and helping keep our kids
safe the Frankie Smith Funeral Home in
cremator in Lancaster and the Johnson
Smith Funeral Home in Baltimore have a
long and wonderful history of serving
our community feel free to give us a
call at
0652 stop in and see us at either of our
two locations 405 North Columbus Street
in Lancaster and 207 South Main Street
in Baltimore respect for tradition
regard for
[Music]
change
e for